Name: Gareth Thomas Address: 34 New Mill Street

> Eccleston Chorley

Lancashire, PR7 5FT

E-Mail: gareth a thomas@hotmail.com

Tel: 07507550152

Gareth has over 10 years senior commercial management experience within the Construction and Engineering industry and has demonstrated strong commercial skills during this period, particularly in relation to developing client relationships, business development, revenue maximisation and profit improvement. He has excellent communication skills with a proven track record in the ability to communicate with a wide range of people. Skilled, passionate and honest senior manager and keen to add value to all aspects of the business he is part of. He has demonstrable experience of working under NEC and ICC forms of contracts and have a proven ability of setting up and running business units and projects alike.

## **EDUCATION AND QUALIFICATIONS**

2009 ILM Level 5 in Leadership & Management

2004 Runshaw College (CIM)

CIM Certificate in Marketing - Merit

1998 – 2000 University of Salford

BA (Hons) Applied Consumer Studies - 2.2

1996 – 1998 University of Salford

**HND Applied Consumer Studies - Merit** 

**EXPERIENCE** 

Kier plc November 2013 – June 2019

Senior Commercial Manager July 2016 – June 2019

Overseeing and support across all contracts within the Highways Division (Suffolk Highways, Harrow Highways, Street Lighting Business, Surface Treatments Business, Surrey Highways, Highways England). Providing centralised commercial support which included: Profit Improvement Plans & Delivery, Cash Improvement, Innovations, Bid Support, Contract Mobilisations (Shropshire Highways Term Maintenance Contract - £25m per annum), Dispute Resolutions, Implementation of Procurement Strategies, Corporate Governance.

Regional Commercial Manager November 2013 – June 2016

Day to day commercial management of Lincolnshire Highways Term Maintenance Contract with an annual value of £45m per annum. In addition to this core contract I was involved in

the delivery of external third party work, in which some instances totalled in excess of £5m per annum.

Lincolnshire Highways Term Maintenance Contract - £45m per annum (2013 – 2016) Teal Park A46 Lincoln Bypass - £16m (Final Account including mediation with supply chain)

## **Enterprise plc**

June 2004 - November 2013

Commercial Manager

Day to day commercial management of a number of contracts, which included:

Liverpool Council Streetscene Contract (Bundled Highways, Grounds, Streetscene & Waste Contract worth approximately £45m per annum.

Manchester Council Waste Contract - Approximately £12m per annum Selby Council Waste Contract - £2.5m per annum South Ribble Waste Contract - £5m per annum

British Telecom Utility Contract (Overhead Lines, Underground Cabling and Associated Civils works) - £75m per annum

## Commercial Management

- Extensive commercial management experience on Highways, Utilities and Environmental contracts, varying in annual values of between £10m and £50m.
- Experience in a variety of different forms of contract (NEC, JCT etc)
- Full responsibility for profit and loss and working capital for contracts / business units worth in excess of £45m per annum.
- Cost management and service innovation.
- Development and maintenance of contract business plans.
- Commercial lead on other 3<sup>rd</sup> party bids / tenders to increase profitability.
- Responsibility for business development/innovations creating wider opportunities within the appropriate boundaries, whilst also reducing costs for client.
- Cash Management ensure cash / working capital position is maximsed at all times.
- Legal and contractual negotiations with client and supply chain.
- Drafting, reviewing and advising on both client and sub-contractor agreements (including staff secondments).
- Agreement of full and final account settlements of subcontractor and client accounts.
- Direct management of commercial and finance teams.
- Negotiations with Trade Unions and their representatives.
- Experience in TUPE transfers of more than 200 employees.
- Commercial Lead on the mobilisation of new contracts / new service offerings.

## **Business Planning**

- Creation and development of annual business and commercial plans.
- Production of detailed annual budgets in conjunction with both clients and operational teams.
- Production of guarterly forecast reviews, and presentation to divisional boards.
- Review of month end performance with operational colleagues to identify trends and improvement areas.
- Fully detailed commercial & financial risk management planning (please see below)

#### Operational

- Hands on operational involvement on all contracts.
- Worked very closely with all General Managers and took over operational responsibility when unavailable (including in one instance over a 6 month period).
- Heavily involved in decision making processes internally and externally with the client.
- Key stakeholder in planning and executing operational delivery and efficiencies.

## Performance Review & Reporting

- Presentation of commercial and financial performance to divisional board during monthly Business Review Meetings.
- Working Capital Action Plans Improving overall working capital position across a number of contracts / divisional business unit.
- Delivery of best value through efficient commercial practices and procedures (i.e. monthly risk registers, Profit Improvement Plan (PIP) trackers, weekly working capital action plans etc.)
- Production of appropriate budget analysis to both client and business to enable key business decisions to be made.

#### Process Improvements / Development

- Commercial Lead on the migration of two commercial businesses onto one commercial and financial operating system;
- Review and development of commercial processes.
- Delivery of training and communication to all commercial staff.
- Ensure smooth transition between commercial / finance systems.
- Highways Academy Development and delivery of Commercial module "Business Improvement", which is accredited with the Institute of Leadership and Management.

## **Procurement**

- Commercial lead in the procurement of supply chain on all contracts operated on. This
  includes the development of close working relationships to ensure successful delivery
  and service innovations for the client.
- Development of online supply chain on boarding (PQQ) system for the Kier Utilities
   Division.

## Risk Management

- Member of the "Risk Management Committee" for Enterprise Group Holdings Ltd –
  highlighting risk and making recommendations to the main board on changes /
  processes to mitigate potential risk where appropriate.
- Gareth regularly contributes, provides advice and assistance in respect of risk mitigation and strategy.
- Development of detailed contract risk management plans.

#### **Commercial Dispute Resolution**

- Responsibility and conduct of all commercial litigation disputes.
- Reviewing and supporting claim preparation.
- Experience in leading mediations on for claims in excess of £500k.

# **Business Development**

- Working with organisations to develop revenue streams through both central & local government funding as external private sources.
- Support of local authorities, private organisations and charities in obtaining funding through grants, external sponsorship and other commercial activities.

## Other Key Skills / Experience

- Business development Account manager to various schemes (clients such as Liverpool Mutual Homes / CRBE) to deliver best value and optimum standards, whilst developing relationships and winning further work.
- People management providing encouragement, whilst setting challenging but achievable goals and objectives.
- Excellent analytical reporting and planning skills.
- Strong Communication Skills Full understanding of the wider business' requirements and ensuring that these are communicated to clients, employees and members of the stakeholders at all levels.
- Excellent MS Office skills.
- Good understanding of local political pressures Eccleston Parish Councillor between May 2015 and October 2016.
- FA Registered Intermediary (IMS003733). Providing representation and commercial support to professional footballers and clubs.

#### Interests

Gareth's interests include: Football (Spectator, participating, and studying the business element of the industry), golf, reading, travel.